<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- 

  usage.xml            GaussForHomalg package documentation                  Simon Goertzen
                                                                     

         Copyright (C) 2007-2008, Lehrstuhl B für Mathematik, RWTH-Aachen

This chapter explains the usage of this package.

-->

<Chapter Label="usage">
<Heading>Usage</Heading>

If you are just interested in using the &Gauss; package with &homalg;,
you do not need to know much about &GaussForHomalg;, as it will work
in the background, telling &homalg; which functions to call.<P/>

However, you might be interested in writing your own
<Package>XyzForHomalg</Package>, enabling &homalg; to assist you with
your computations. For this purpose, I will provide an overview of the
&GaussForHomalg; code. Please note that &Gauss; is a &GAP; package,
therefore this is not a reference guide for the package
&RingsForHomalg;, which utilizes the IO-stream functionality of &IO_ForHomalg;
to send commands to external computer algebra systems. If you wish to
tie an external system to &homalg;, &RingsForHomalg; is the better
reference package.<P/>

The file for all low-level operations is <F>GaussTools.gi</F>. Like
all "Tools" files it  just includes one global variable
<C>CommonHomalgTableForGaussTools</C>, which is a record of functions
with &homalg; matrices as arguments. The return values of the
&GaussForHomalg; tools are documented in <Ref Label="methods"/> and
have to be the same for each tools table.<P/>

In this particular case, the file also includes the following
code:<P/>

<Listing>if IsBound( HOMALG.OtherInternalMatrixTypes ) then
    Add( HOMALG.OtherInternalMatrixTypes, IsSparseMatrix );
else
    HOMALG.OtherInternalMatrixTypes := [ IsSparseMatrix ];
fi;</Listing>

This is a specialty to explain to &homalg; that &Gauss; introduces a
new matrix type in &GAP;. Usually, there should not be a need for this.<P/>

The next "general" file is <F>GaussBasic.gi</F>. This includes the
basic functions based on <Cite Key="BR"/>, again stored in the global
record <C>CommonHomalgTableForGaussBasic</C>. Preceding this record
are some small methods to make sure &GaussForHomalg; works with sparse
as well as with dense matrices - just like above, these should not be
neccessary in general.<P/>

In <F>GaussForHomalg.gi</F> the methods for matrix entry manipulation
are installed.<P/>

Finally, we come to the most important files, making sense of the
basic functions and tools defined above. Depending on the
functionality (especially concerning function names) of the system you
will need different files for different rings. In this case,
functionality for <M>&ZZ; / n &ZZ;</M> is stored in <F>GaussFQI.gi</F>
(Finite Quotients of the Integers), while the Rationals have their own
file, <F>GaussRationals.gi</F>. Note that both files include only one
method, <C>CreateHomalgTable</C>, using method selection to create the
correct table. Depending on the properties of the ring, the basic
functions are loaded and some more "specific" functions can be
defined, in this case for example the function
<Ref Func="TriangularBasisOfRows"/>, both in a one- and a two-argument
version. The tools should be universal enough to be loaded for every
possible ring. If it is neccessary to overwrite a tool, this is the
place to do it. An example for this could be <Ref Func="Involution"/>,
which is generally just a matrix transposition, but could be
overwritten to be a true involution when creating the &homalg; table
for noncommutative rings.

</Chapter>
